Guide to the Keith Johnstone Papers SC1210
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Keith Johnstone papers
1953-2007
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Johnstone, Keith.
SC1210
9 Linear Feet (6 cartons)
Original plays, writings, correspondence, theatrical materials, journals, and artwork..
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Keith Johnstone is a British and Canadian pioneer of improvisational theatre, best known for inventing the Impro System, part of which are the Theatresports. He is also an educator, playwright, actor and theatre director.
Keith's ideas about improvisation, behaviour and performance appeal to a wide variety of groups. From actors to psychotherapists, improvisation companies to theatre schools and companies, business and management training specialists and humanities research institutes, universities and film production companies have invited him to come to teach them about his ideas, and how they might apply them.
Born February, 1933, in Devon, England, Johnstone grew up hating school, finding that it blunted his imagination and made him feel self-conscious and shy. In the late 1950s, as a play-reader, director and drama teacher at the Royal Court Theatre in London, he chose to reverse all that his teachers had told him in an attempt to create more spontaneous actors. In the 1970s, Johnstone moved to Calgary, Alberta to teach at the University of Calgary.
He founded the Theatre Machine Improvisation group in England in the 1960's, touring Europe and North America. Johnstone co-founded the Loose Moose Theatre, and invented his system of training that has been influencing practice within and beyond the traditional theatre for over 50 years. His system include formats such as "Gorilla Theatre", "Micetro" or "Maestro", and "Life Game". The latter has been seen at the National Theatre courtesy of Improbable Theatre, and on U.S. cable television. He founded The International Theatresports™ Institute in 1998.
Johnston has written two books about his system; Impro: Improvisation and the Theatre (1979), and Impro For Storytellers (1999).
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of original plays, writings, correspondence, theatrical materials, journals, and artwork.
Comedy; Comedy sketches; Improvisation (Acting); Theatre -- History; Close, Del -- Correspondence; Coyote, Peter. -- Correspondence; Beckett, Samuel -- Correspondence; Johnstone, Keith.; Pinter, Harold -- Correspondence
- Plays
  - Sketches, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "They Came by the Night" Original with Revisions (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Best of Unzipped (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unzipped Further (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unzipped One, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Unzipped (Rev. Prod. Copy), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marg (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Damian (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Geronimo (English and Danish Versions) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Last Bird, Circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Last Bird (With Revisions), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Last Bird (Copy), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Last Bird (Copy) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Last Bird (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Last Bird (Rewrites after Production), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Last Bird (With Edits), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Last Bird (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Last Bird, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Last Bird (Incomplete Copy) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Den Sidste Fugl (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Men and Angels (Short Story Based on The Last Bird) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Last Bird, 2004 May (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Live Snakes and Ladders (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Martian (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mindswop Pre-Production Draft, 1983 Mar (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mindswop (Original) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mindswop (rough draft), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Moby Dick (2 Revisions from Previous Years) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Moby Dick, Circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mutiny on the Bounty (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Nigger Hunt, 1958 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gloomy Go Round (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Suit + The De-Programmer, 1997 Jun (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Play Mor56 (Synopsis) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Attempts at Plays (Several Unfinished Projects) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Beast with Five Fingers (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brixham Regatta (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brixham Regatta (2/6) Early Drafts (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brixham Regatta (3/6) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brixham Regatta (4/6) Early Draft (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brixham Regatta (5/6) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brixam Regatta (6/6) Early Drafts (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Loose Moose Children's Shows (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clowning at RCT, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Cord (1/6) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Cord (2/6), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Cord (3/6) 4 Revisions/Drafts (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Cord (4/6), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Cord (5/6) Revisions, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Cord (6/6) Swedish Translation, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Defeat of Grant Bignose (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Faust's Angel (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - For Children - Earliest Draft, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Frog Wife, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Invitation (Includes Danish Version) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jeremy & The Timber Box, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Performing Giants (1/2) Original Script (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Performing Giants (2/2) Incomplete Scripts and Drafts, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Adaptations, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Robinson Crusoe (2 Scripts), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Version 1) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Edits) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Robinson Crusoe (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The Secret Life of Dr. Watson, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Secret Life of Dr. Watson (Original with edits and revisions) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - The Secret Life of Dr. Watson (Revision), 1997 Jun (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Shot by an Elk (Not Complete) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Shot by an Elk (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Shot By an Elk (Danish Translation), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sir and Perkins Plays (Moby Dick and They Came by the Night), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sir & Perkins - Home (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Sir & Perkins (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Sir & Perkins (Plays, Drafts, etc.) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Home (Sir & Perkins) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Time Marchine (Sir & Perkins) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sir & Perkins (Plays, drafts, etc.) (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Other Writings
  - Artwork, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Artwork and Comics (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Doodles, 1979-1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Photos (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Theatresports Book, 1996 July (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Theatresports Book, 1996 Jul (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Theatresports Book, 1996 Jul (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Masks (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fast food Stanislavsky Lists (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Connections, 1981-2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photos - Live Snakes & Ladders, Proof Sheets, Negatives (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Other Productions, Circa 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Other Productions - Reviews, 1973-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Misc. Personal Docs, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Godot, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Cinema, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Articles About Keith, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Articles Which Inspired Keith's Teaching (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Pedagogy (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Published Writings, 1965-1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rehearsal Notes (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Royal Court, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Teaching Internationally, 1993-2007 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Theatre Machine (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Misc. Teaching, 1965-2007 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Tempest (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - University of Calgary Correspondence (Teaching), Circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - University of Calgary and Sabbatical Applications, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Misc Teaching, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Teaching Student Material, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - The Stain (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Man on the Beach (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Monastery (Original), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Cord (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - The Monastery, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - This is War (Essay) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Drafts of Newsletters, etc. (News Three) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Drafts of Newletters, etc (Being There) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Drafts of Newsletters, etc. (Journey Without Maps) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Drafts of Newsletters, etc. (Book of the Moses) (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Misc. Writing (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Theatre Design (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Poetry (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Writings on MASKS (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Notes (Impro) (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Early Drafts of Impro Sections (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Status, 1973 Jul (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Pilot (Colour) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "Spontaneity" & "Narrative Skills" Chapters of IMPRO (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Status Essay (Rough Copy) (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Account of Student at Summer School who he mentions in IMPRO in section "A Psychotic Girl" (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Trance & Masks" Chapter in IMPRO (Original Copy) (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Loose Moose Materials, 1983-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Loose Moose Materials (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Loose Moose Materials, Circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Moose Art Original (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - International Festival, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Loose Moose Drawings (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lifegame (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Vancouver, Theatersports, League - Legal Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters - Theatreports & Lifegames, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Performance Advances, 1994 Dec (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Theatresports, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Other Theatresports Companies, 1985-1999 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Loose Moose - Misc., 1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Theatresports - Misc., 1982-1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Loose Moose Publicity (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Loose Moose Newspaper Clippings, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The Knack - Programs & Posters (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Misc. RCT Docs (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Theatre Machine, 1966-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Day of the Prince" by Frank Hilton, RCT 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - End Game (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Performing Giant, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Misc. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Misc. Docs (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Short Story "The Return", 1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Short Stories & early "Brixham Regatta", 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Short Stories, 1955-1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Wallet and clippings (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Wallet and clippings (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Wallet and clippings (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Correspondence
  - Academia, 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Former Students, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - to Critics, 1982-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Important Connections, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Inquires & Misc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, Thank yous (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Contracts, 1983-2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Loose Moose, 1979-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Mentors (Stirling, Bell, etc.) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Misc. Professional, 1978-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - RCT Personal, 1960-2006 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - RCT (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Theatre Machine, 1976-2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Theatresports + Concepts, 1984-1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Personal, 1969-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letters, 1960-1999 (Box 4, Folder 16)